<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of instituted churches explained and proved from the word of God by Solomon Stoddard ...</title>
            <author>Stoddard, Solomon, 1643-1729.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16977</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13034293</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13034293</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96810</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96810)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 400:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of instituted churches explained and proved from the word of God by Solomon Stoddard ...</title>
                  <author>Stoddard, Solomon, 1643-1729.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ralph Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: filmed copy dark and difficult to read.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregational churches --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96810:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96810:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF <hi rend="blackletterType">Inſtituted Churches</hi> Explained and Proved FROM THE WORD OF GOD</p>
            <p>By <hi rend="blackletterType">Solomon Stoddard,</hi> A. M. <hi>Minister</hi> of the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Northampton, New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the Bible under the <hi>Piaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Exchange in Cornhil.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96810:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96810:2"/>
            <head>THE DOCTRINE OF Inſtituted CHURCHES Explained, and Proved from the WORD of GOD.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Word of God gives us ſufficient Light, to direct us about Inſtituted Churches and all Adminiſtrations therein.</head>
               <p>THE Nature of an Inſtituted Church and the Ordinances to be attended therein, have been matter of great Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in theſe latter Ages. And thoſe Inquiries have been Accompanied with great Animoſities, Diſcords and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions: Thoſe forms and methods that have been admired by ſome, have been decryed by others, and Multitudes of People are left at a loſs whether there be any certain Rule to Guide us; or any certainty to be attained in theſe things.</p>
               <p>Two things eſpecially have hindred thoſe that have been ſtudious in theſe points, from giving ſatisfaction to others: One of them is, that ſome of them have been exceeding tenacious of the Traditions and Ancient uſages of the Church, not conſidering how diſmal a Corruption and Degeneracy did in a little time prevail: whereby it comes to paſs that thoſe things are obtruded upon us as Rules, which were the Blemiſhes and Errors of the Ancient Church: They have a Veneration for antiquity and adopt the ſayings of Ancient
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96810:3"/> Fathers for Canonical. The other is, that ſome have attempted to compile a compleat Platform, out of the Books of the NewTeſtament alone, looking on all Old Teſtament Rules, relating to Church Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as out of Date: but if we would have a right underſtanding of the mind of God in theſe things, muſt not be our dependance upon traditions, neither muſt we confine our ſelves to one part of Scripture, but ſearch into the whole Word of God impartially.</p>
               <p>It is certain that God does fully direct us in the Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Affairs of his Houſe; as the Word of God doth perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly direct us how we ſhould behave our ſelves in the Family and in the Common-wealth, ſo in the Church: There is no need of any Addition to the Scriptures: There needs an Interpretation of the Word, but nothing at all to be added to it: God doth not give us ſome broken pieces of a Platform; but hath revealed his whole will in that matter: We are not left under a neceſſity of miſſing the Rule or gueſſing at it. God hath deſcribed to us the whole Body of Church Affairs: <hi>For the Scripture is a perfect Rule of Life,</hi> Pſal. 19.7. 2 Tim. 3.17,18. <hi>Men ſhall be blamed for nothing at the Day of Judgment, but what the Scripture does Condemn,</hi> Rev. 20.12. <hi>VVhat God hath not revealed to us, is no Rule to us: And God hath no where elſe revealed the Rule but in the Scripture.</hi> As we have no extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prophets to reveal the mind of God; So there are no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written traditions to make known the mind of God in this matter.</p>
               <p>There be three ſorts of Rules in Scripture to guide us in Church Affairs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>General Moral Rules:</hi> Theſe Rules give us light in many Church Affairs: <hi>So that Rule of Loving God and our Neighbour,</hi> Mat. 22.37,38,39. <hi>So that Rule of not partaking in other Mens Sins,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22. <hi>So that Rule of Peace and Edification,</hi> Rom. 14.19,20. <hi>So that Rule of doing things decently and in order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.20. <hi>So that Rule,</hi> Phil. 4.8. <hi>So that Rule of Humility,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.3. <hi>Theſe Rules and ſuch like ſhew us our Duty in many Caſes. For,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There be many things neceſſary which there is no Inſtitution about: God was more particular with the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe the Church then was in its Infancy, than he is with us: So we have no inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how many Elders to have in a Church, how often to Pray or Sing on the Sabbath: <hi>How often to partake of the Lords Supper,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. So there is no particular inſtitution for Moderators in Churches, in caſe of a vacancy of Elders: About Preaching without ordination: About the Limits and Bounds of particular Churches: There be abundance of other particulars, about Faſts, matters of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96810:3"/> Diſcipline, the Age of Perſons to be admitted to the Lords Supper; which are to be determined by Moral Rules.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many things that are commanded in Church Affairs are the proper conſequences of Moral Rules: And ſo don't need an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: There be many things occaſionally commanded: Which do not properly belong to Divine inſtitutions, that are not Branches of the ſecond Commandment, but proper deduction from Moral Rules; So that about Reconciliation to an offended Brother, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.23,24. <hi>For Chriſt did not now make new Jewiſh inſtitutions:</hi> So that about private dealing with an offending Brother, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15,16. So thoſe Rules, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17,19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. And many others are plain Moral Duties.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Moral Rules muſt be attended in Church Affairs as well as in other things: Rules for doing things that are for Peace, Edification, and for the good of our Neighbours, bind in Eccleſiaſtical caſes as well as in Civil and Domeſtical: Therefore they are Generally Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Yea, there is more weight to be laid on them, then on inſtitutions, Mar.</hi> 12.33. We muſt never Act contrary to Moral Rules; Churches are bound to Moral Rules, as well as other Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: We have n2o liberty in the Adminiſtration of the things of Gods Houſe to break Moral Rules.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Old Teſtament inſtitutions: A great part of Old Teſtament inſtitutions are aboliſhed: All typical Laws are out of Date: But ſome inſtitutions that were in force then are in force now: Thus Church Societies, the Preaching of the Word, Faſts, Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, are to be attended ſtill. Conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They and we are under the ſame Goſpel, there was the ſame way of Salvation then as now, they were under a Covenant of Grace and Saved by Chriſt as well as we, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. Hence there be ſeveral things common to them and us: Hence the People of God under the Old and New Teſtament muſt be ſuch as have a viſible Union to Chriſt; they and we muſt have ſigns repreſenting Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3,4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Nature of a Church is the ſame under both Teſtaments: A Church is not one kind of thing in the Old Teſtament and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the New: But it has the ſame eſſence and definition: The matter of the Church and the form is the ſame: The Church then ſtood in the ſame relation to God, was appointed for Communion with God, and enjoyed his preſence as now.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There were ſeveral Ordinances in the Jewiſh Church, that had no particular reference to the times before Chriſt; or to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular condition of that People: And ſuch Ordinances ſeem to be of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96810:4"/> force ſtill, as their, having an holy Convocation, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.13. So, much of the work of the Prieſts, they were to teach the People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.10. They were to bleſs the People, <hi>Num.</hi> 6.23. So it was their manner in ſolemn Prayer and Bleſſing to lay on hands: So Excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which is to continue in the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We are referred in ſome caſes to thoſe inſtitutions: God ſends us to the Law for light, directs us to do as was appointed in the Old Teſtament: So about Womens not ſpeaking in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. So about the maintenance of Miniſters, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13,14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. New Teſtament inſtitutions, there were ſome inſtitutions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt under the Goſpel, theſe are few; principally, what Officers ſhall be in the Church, <hi>The Sacraments of Baptiſm, and the Lords Supper, and the firſt day Sabbath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt diſtinguiſh between Temporal and Perpetual inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Some inſtitutions were only for a time, as the Office of the Apoſtles: <hi>So the anointing of the ſick with Oyl, Jam.</hi> 5.14. There are others that are to continue to the end of the World: <hi>So is Baptiſm,</hi> Matth. 20. <hi>The Lords Supper,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. Theſe Ordinances will not be removed as <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.28.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Diſtinguiſh between approved practiſes and inſtitutions, there were many practiſes and inſtitutions, there were many practiſes in the primitive times that were approved, yet not binding to us: The Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had ſeven Deacons, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.5. <hi>They did Baptize in private Houſes,</hi> Act. 10.33. <hi>Chriſt ſent out his Diſciples two and two,</hi> Luk. 10.1. This doth not ſhew that theſe things were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions; that is meet to be done in one caſe, that is not meet to be done in another: One or two Examples ſhew the Lawfulneſs of a practiſe, but do not make it a binding Rule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96810:4"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. The Nature of Inſtituted Churches Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</head>
               <p>THE Word <hi>Church</hi> is uſed Equivocally, there are three ſenſes eſpecially, wherein it is uſed in the Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is taken for thoſe that are Spiritually United unto Chriſt, the miſtical Body of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. <hi>That he might preſent it to himſelf a Glorious Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> For that part of the World that doth profeſs the true faith for them that are viſible Chriſtians, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.9. <hi>I perſecuted the Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is taken for an Inſtituted Church; this Church is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted by Chriſt with Spiritual Power and is thus defined: A Church is a Society of Saints joyned tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther, according to the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt for the conſtant carrying on of his publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: A Church is a Society, a ſingle Perſon is not a Church, a Church is a Collection or Congregative Body, conſiſting of many Members, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. Ye are the Body of Chriſt and Members in particulars, hence it is compared to a flock and other C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ective Bodies: It is a Society of Saints, <hi>The Members of a Church are Saints by calling,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.12. To the Church of God which is at <hi>Corinth,</hi> to them, which are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. <hi>In all the Churches of the Saints, the Church of the</hi> Jews <hi>was a Society of Saints,</hi> Pſal. 79.12,11. Pſal. 1. <hi>None are to be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Inſtituted Churches, but thoſe that are Members of the Catholick Church.</hi> Particular Churches are but parts and branches of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, they are the Churches of God, the Body of Chriſt, the Temple of God, therefore muſt be Holy. <hi>Therefore Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Papiſts are abuſively called Churches:</hi> A Church doth joyn together for the Publick carrying on of the Worſhip of God: A Family joyning together for the private carrying on of the Worſhip of God is not a Church; we read of a Church in the Houſe of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, Rom.</hi> 16.5. And in the Houſe of <hi>Nymphas, Col.</hi> 4.15. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there the publick Worſhip of God was attended: The Church doth joyn, for the carrying on of publick Worſhip; as the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, the Adminiſtration of Sacraments and diſpenſing of Cenſures in a publick way.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96810:5"/>
               <p>A Church doth joyn together for the conſtant carrying on of the publick Worſhip of God, for a Church is a Body Corporate, which may continue from Generation to Generation, it is not any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Meeting together, that gives being to a Church: A Church is a ſtanding Society, not depending on any occaſional Meeting; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Congregation that meet together on a Lecture Day, from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Towns to hear the Word Preached are not a Church, neither have any Eccleſiaſtical Power: Yea, a ſynod that meet now and then occaſionally, though it may be called a repreſentative Church, is not a Church properly; the Members thereof are choſen for a perticular occaſion: A Church doth joyn together according to Chriſts appointment; Chriſt has given a Rule according to which they ought to joyn together, and if Men joyn in Worſhiping with a Church irregularly, that does not make them to be Members of that Church: If a man that lives in one Town where there is a Church, doth joyn conſtantly in worſhiping with another Church, that doth not make him a Member of that Church.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVho are viſible Saints?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Queſtion hath been matter of great debate, and an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of great contention in the Church; we may not count thoſe only to be Saints, who after the ſtricteſt Examination, give conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable evidence that they are Saints: We have no ſuch Rule, the practice of the Apoſtles in admitting Members into the Chriſtian Church doth not Countenance any ſuch Opinion, neither are we to make Baptized Perſons and Viſible Saints to be the ſame; for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt be Viſible Saints before they are Baptized; and ſome that are Baptized, may ceaſe to be Viſible Saints; neither are they only Viſible Saints, that make a profeſſion of the true Religion joyned with an Holy Converſation: Some Men may behave themſelves ſo as to deſerve a ſentence of Excommunication, and yet be Viſible Saints: Viſible Saintſhip and real Saintſhip, may conſiſt with a great deal of iniquity in the Converſation for a time.</p>
               <p>Viſible Saints are ſuch as make a ſerious profeſſion of the true Religion, together with thoſe that do deſcend from them, till rejected of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such as do make a ſerious profeſſion of the true Religion, are Viſible Saints; we find the Apoſtles did really accept of ſuch, not waiting to ſee, what their Converſation would be, <hi>Act.</hi> 16,14,15. So did <hi>John,</hi> Luk. 7.29,30. <hi>Such are to be accepted without delay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Their Infant Seed are likewiſe Viſible Saints, God gives that Teſtimony for them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96810:5"/>
               <p n="3">3. Such alſo as deſcend from them, from Generation to Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, untill they are rejected by God are Viſible Saints for they that are Viſible Saints don't ceaſe to be ſo, till God hath caſt them off; So it was with the Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> if they ſhould carry it wickedly, or if they ſhould fall into Hereſy, yet they are Viſible Saints, till God hath rejected them; and there are two ways whereby God may ſhew his rejection of them: One is when they do depart from the Churches of God to Heathen or Antichriſtian Societies, the other is, when the People that they belong unto and they with them are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churched by God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the Nature of a Congregational Church.</head>
               <p>AS a Civil Society doth conſiſt of one Town, or more Towns, ſo an inſtituted Church is either Congregational, or that which conſiſts of Divers Congregations.</p>
               <p>A Congregational Church is a Church that is bound by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God to aſſemble together in one place in a conſtant way for the Celebration of his Publick Worſhip; A Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church, is a Church conſiſting of one Congregation: Such we read of, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23. The form of a Congregational Church is, that they are bound by the appointment of God to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble in one place in a conſtant way for the Celebration of his Publick Worſhip. Some have thought that the form of a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Church is a Church Covenant, explicite or implicite, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they bind themſelves to walk together according to the order of the Goſpel. It is thought that the Children of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Covenanting with God is a Foundation for this whereas that Covenant of theirs is no other, then what all Chriſtians do make, when they make a profeſſion of Faith and Obedience; we never read of any parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Covenant made in the Synagogues, which Anſwer to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, whereby the Members of one Synagogue were bound one to another: It is pleaded that nothing elſe can bind a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple one to another but an Eccleſiaſtical Covenant; but there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe that binds a free People in the ſame Town to mutual ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, to the Government of the Town; and tho Chriſtians are a free People, yet they have not a Licentious Liberty but are bound
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96810:6"/> by God, and likewiſe by their own profeſſion to the Rule of the Goſpel: Neither is there any neceſſity of ſuch a bond to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh one Church from another, and to avoid confuſion of Churches, we read of no ſuch particular Covenant in the New Teſtament, we have no precept for it, we have no preſident for it; we read of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Congregational Churches, but there is no Syllable in the Word of God, intimating any ſuch thing, neither is there any need of it.</p>
               <p>The Members of a Congregation are bound to carry on the Worſhip together, this is Gods appointment, that his People that live together ſhould carry on his Worſhip together, the Chriſtians at <hi>Corinth</hi> are the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. And the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at <hi>Epheſus</hi> are the Church of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> Order calls for it, that where Men live, there they joyn together to carry on the Work of Chriſt. If a Chriſtian live in a Town, where there is a Church, he is immediately bound to joyn with that Church; and that Church is bound to him to govern him, and give him Chriſtian Priviledges; there be ſome caſes wherein there is need of humane prudence in determining how many Churches ſhall be in ſome Towns: Some Towns ariſe to be numerous, ſo that it is fit they ſhould be joyned in ſeveral Societies: And ſome are ſo ſmall and lye ſo near together, that it is fit that two or more ſhould make one Church, in ſuch caſes God has appointed that the bounds of Churches be ſet either by General agreement, or by order from Authority, but there is no occaſion that every Member ſhould Covenant particularly with the Church: Grant this particular Covenant to be the form of a Church, and then a Chriſtian may continue a conſiderable time, without any relation to a particular Church, tho he lives, where there is a Church: And then a Man may be a Member of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years together, and live all that while in Communion with the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> a Covenant which he lives in the continual breach of, makes a Member at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and according to ſome, gives him a right to all Ordinances: Grant this particular Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and we ſhall be to ſeek, what Church many Children do belong to, the father is in Covenant with one Church, the Mother with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Child was Baptized in a third and lives in a fourth: This Doctrine of the particular Covenant which is wholly unſcriptural, is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on that many among us are ſhut out of the Church, to whom Church Priviledges do belong.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96810:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. of the Priviledges of Congregational Churches.</head>
               <p>THE great Priviledge of Congregational Churches is to chooſe their own Officers, they have a liberty given to them by God to chooſe ſuteable Perſons to Office, they are limited to Perſons fitly qualified, but the Priviledge of chooſing them doth belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, it is very probable, that the Synagognes of the <hi>Yews</hi> had liberty to chooſe their own Miniſters; if they were confined to the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> yet out of the Levites they chooſe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; However, thus it ought to be in Chriſtian Churches, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ordered the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to chooſe their own Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3,4. They did not take upon them to preſcribe, who the Perſons ſhould be, and impoſe Deacons on them, but referred the matter to their own choice; and the People nominated two, out of which God choſe one to be an Apoſtle, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.23.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it is the Priviledge of all free Societies to chooſe their own Officers; ſuch Countrys as are conquer'd don't chuſe their own Rulers, nor ſuch Countrys where the Government is Hereditary, but ſuch as are free, neither under the Power of Conqueroes, nor the Bond of a Covenant do chooſe their own Officers either mediately or immediately: All the Power that Men have over a free People is by their own conſent, directly or indirectly, excepting ſuch caſes wherein God is pleaſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oint Rulers, or ſome who ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Rulers over them; God appointed <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Poſterity to the Office of the Prieſthood in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but God hath not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed any Officers in Churches now, neither hath he appointed any that ſhall impoſe Officers over them, but hath left them to their free choice.</p>
               <p>Yea, where a Church hath teaching, or Ruling Elders, or both, there is no neceſſity that they ſhould conſent to the choice, if they do not conſent, yet if there be the conſent of the Major part, the choice is vallid; the Officers ought to ſubmit thereto, unleſs they have ſome weighty Objection, the Act of the Major part, is the Act of the Community, that which is the Priviledge of the Community,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96810:7"/> muſt not be wreſted out of their hands; It is beyond the Power of the Officers to diſanul their Act.</p>
               <p>And as the Church hath Power to chooſe their own Officers, ſo in caſe of need they have Power to chooſe thoſe that ſhall ſupply the want of Officers for a time, the Church is entruſted with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Power in order to the carrying on of Gods work: Therefore in caſe of the vacancy of a Paſtor, they may chooſe one to Preach to them for a time, in caſe they have no Elders, they may chooſe a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator; In caſe they have no Deacons they may chooſe one to do the Deacons work, yea in caſe there be need, they may chooſe ſome other Miniſter of the Goſpel, to Adminiſter the Seals of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or perform ſome Act of Government upon a particular occaſion.</p>
               <p>By the ſame reaſon that a Church may chooſe its own Officers, it may alſo chooſe its own Servants; <hi>Phebe</hi> is called a Servant of the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2. So were Widdows, for they were not ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; So their Sexton and ſuch as ſhall over-ſee the Buildings, or any other Servants that may be for the conveniency of the Church. This Church Priviledge of chooſing Officers, doth only belong to the Brethren of the Church, the Brethren are ſaid to chooſe the Deacons, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3. <hi>And Women have not Power in this matter,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.33. <hi>Let your Women keep ſilence in the Churches,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.12. Suffer not a Woman to teach, nor to uſurp Authority over the Man, it is inconſiſtent with that State of ſubjection which God hath put them into, if they might vote, they might over-rule the Men, and by the ſame Rule, thoſe Males that are not their own Maſters, (as Children that are not at their own diſpoſe, and Servants) have nothing to do to vote in the Church they that are not free, are not to partake of this Liberty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Of the Officers of Congregational Churches and their Power.</head>
               <p>THE Officers of Congregational Churches are either Elders or Deacons, the Elders are either teaching Elders, or Ruling Elders. The work of the Teaching Elders lies principally in theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96810:7"/> five things; they are to be the mouth of the People to God, both in the publick Aſſembly, and privately in caſe of ſickneſs, they are to Preach the Word of God, they are to Adminiſter the Seals of the Covenant, they together with the Ruling Elders, are to Govern the Church, and they are to bleſs the People.</p>
               <p>Such Learned Men as are ſuteably qualified, but not in Office may upon occaſion diſcharge ſome part of this work; but there are ſome other parts of it, that they may not meddle with, thoſe Acts which are Acts of Natural Worſhip may be performed by them, as pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Preaching; but ſuch Miniſterial Acts as do depend wholly upon inſtitution, they may not perform, as the Adminiſtration of Sacraments, the diſpencing of Cenſures and an Authoritative bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; theſe are performed only by Virtue of an Inſtitution, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are to be done only according to an Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>A teaching Elder by Virtue of his relation to a particular Church, is bound to attend his work in that Church: And by Virtue of that relation, he has no Authority to perform Acts of Office to any other Church, or to the Members of any other Church Aſſembling with his own Church: Paſtoral Power over a particular Church gives him no Power over any that are of that Church, his relation to them gives him no Power over any other.</p>
               <p>But every Man that is a Paſtor of a particular Church ſtands in a more General relation, as a Miniſter of Chriſt; ſome that are not Paſtors to particular Congregations are yet Miniſters of Chriſt; and every Man that is a Paſtor to a particular Church is a Miniſter of Chriſt, and by Virtue of that Relation he may do Acts of Office to the Members of other Churches occaſionally aſſembling with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> own, and towards other Churches being deſired, when he can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently be ſpared from his own, and towards particular Perſons that are Members of no Church.</p>
               <p>The Levites were the Miniſters of God before they had Relation to any particular Synagogue; <hi>Paul</hi> hath Office Power over the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as well as the Church of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.17,18. The Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſent <hi>Barnabas</hi> to <hi>Antiock,</hi> to officiate as a Miniſter, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. And they that have Authority to Preach have alſo to Baptize, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19,20. We find that <hi>Paul</hi> did not Baptize ſuch as he brought over to the Chriſtian faith, but committed that work to ſome other inferiour Miniſters that were in Company with him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14. And this he did after the Example of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 4.2. There is need that ſome have Office-Power now to Preach to the Heathens, as well as there was in the Days of the Apoſtles, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96810:8"/> there may be ſeveral now that Baptiſm doth belong to; as well as <hi>Cornelius,</hi> the Eunuch and the Jallor and others, therefore there are ſome appointed by God for that Service.</p>
               <p>The Teaching Officer is appointed by Chriſt to Baptize and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Lords Supper, and therefore he is made the Judge by God, what Perſons thoſe ordinances are to be Adminiſtred to, and it is not the work either of the Brethren or Ruling Elders, any ways to intermeddle in that Affair or Limit him; we never read that the Apoſtles did adviſe with the Church, whether they ſhould Baptize ſuch as offered themſelves. As the Adminiſtration of theſe ordinances is committed to them, ſo the Judging concerning thoſe who they are to be Adminiſtred unto, as they are to Judge what ſubject to teach upon, and as the Deacon is to Judge who is to be relieved; So the Miniſter is to Judge who is to be Baptized and Admitted to the Lords Supper. The Ruling Elders are to joyn with the Teaching Elders in Rule and Government; theſe Officers are called Governments, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Such as Rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. Diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſuch as Labour in the Word and Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. The Teaching Elders with the Ruling Elders, make the Presbytery of the Church; with whom the Government of the Church is entruſted: The Power of Cenſuring offenders in the Church, and abſolving of Penitents, doth belong alone to theſe, the Brethren of the Church are not to intermeddle with it. The Elders are to Rule over the Church, and therefore not to be over-ruled by the Brethren, it is the work of the Elders to rule well, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. The Members of the Church are to be obedient to the Elders, therefore not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul them in their Government, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. The Elders of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, had the Power of Government of the Church in their hands, hence we read of the Rulers and Chief Rulers of the Synagogues, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.5. The Elders have the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven committed to them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. The meaning is, that he ſhould be an Elder and Ruler of the Church, it is ſpoken of as a Perſonal reward of his profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Tell it to the Church, this implies the Power of the Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By the Church is meant the Eccleſiaſtical Authority in diſtinction from the Civil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not harſh by the Church to intend the Elders of the Church. See, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.25.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the Church muſt be meant the Elders of the Church; for this was a Rule in the Day when it was ſpoken, and there was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96810:8"/> now no Church in Being, but the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; in which all the Power of Government was with the Elders.</p>
               <p>Obj. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1,4. <hi>The Church was ordered to caſt out the Inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſon, and</hi> 2 Cor. 12. <hi>His Puniſhment is ſaid to be inflicted by many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. They may be only required to publiſh a ſentence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication from <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is common in Scripture, to attribute that which is done by the Ruler to the Publick Society; as when God requires that the People of <hi>Judah</hi> do Acts of Publick Juſtice, he doth not intend that the People ſhould intrude into that work, but that the Ruler do it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas it is ſaid that the Puniſhment was inflicted by many, it may be read before many; Deacons were choſen at firſt to have an over-ſight of the Poor, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. And there is nothing plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be their work beſides that. It is intimated, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8. That it is their work to ſhew mercy and to give; It is Generally put upon them to take care about the Miniſters dues, and about the Proviſion for the Lords Table, which is gathered from that phraſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2. It is not meet that we ſhould leave the Word of God and ſerve Tables, but there ſeems to be no neceſſity, that there muſt be a Church Officer to do; all that work which the Church is to ſee done; ſome things may be done by Servants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of the Ordination of Church Officers.</head>
               <p>THere are none to be ordained Officers in the Church of God, but thoſe that have a regular call to thoſe Offices; Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the Admiſſion of Perſons into their Office, or the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their call, needful to the regular Execution of their Office; it includes in it firſt, a ſolemn imploring of the preſence of God with them in their Office.</p>
               <p>Two things are requiſite unto a call; One is, the approbation or invitation of thoſe whom God hath entruſted with that care; the other is, the conſent of the Perſon invited; the former may be a call to the latter, and bind the Perſon to accept, but there muſt be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96810:9"/> both, before he is called of God to enter immediately upon the work of the Office; before he be accepted of God as an Officer.</p>
               <p>The work of the Deacon being confined to one Congregation, the invitation of that Church, is ſufficient without any further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.7.</p>
               <p>God having appointed all his Holy Ordinances to be Adminiſtred in a particular Church; in caſe of neceſſity, the choice of a Church is ſufficient (without any further approbation) unto the calling of Elders, as when <hi>Luther</hi> and others broke off from Popery.</p>
               <p>Yet Elders having not only Power over their particular Churches, but alſo over others, and God having committed to National and Provincial Churches, the care of particular Congregations, it is requiſite, when it may be obtained, that there be an approbation of Men choſen to be Elders, by ſome deputed by the National or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Church.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, ſome Perſons being to be entruſted with the Office of being Miniſters of Chriſt, who have no call to any particular Congregation, there is need that they have the approbation of ſome deputed by the Church in that Country, or at leaſt by a particular Congregation: The Perſons that are to perform this Act of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ought to be ſuch as are moſt ſuitable to the Ends of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>viz.</hi> The ſignifying approbation and the obtaining the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God with him; ſometimes we find that extraordinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have ordained a Perſon to extraordinary Office, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. Sometimes we find that extraordinary Perſons have ordained ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. And there is command given to extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Officers to ordain ordinary, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we find that extraordinary Officers, and ordinary have joyned in the ordaining of extraordinary; <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1,5. Sometimes we find that ordinary Officers, have ordained an extraordinary Officer; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. In a Provincial Church that is in order, Miniſters ought to be ordained by ſuch Elders, as are appointed by the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Eccleſiaſtical Authority of the Land.</p>
               <p>In ſuch Countrys where the Church is not in order, it is meet that the Miniſters be ordained by ſome ſuiteable Perſons deputed by the Neighbouring Elders, but in caſe of neceſſity, Miniſters may be ordained by ſome of the Brethren appointed by the Church to that ſervice.</p>
               <p>The Ordination of Deacons ought to be performed by Elders of the ſame Church, in caſe there be any, or by the Brethren in caſe there be none.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96810:9"/>
               <p>A Miniſter removing from one Church to another, may be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a ſecond time, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, and probably <hi>Timothy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the manner in ſome places to give to Churches at their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and to Miniſters at their Ordination, the right hand of fellowſhip, from the Example of the Apoſtles; but it may be doubted whether that was any more then a civil Act, if it be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, we are to ſeek whether it be to be done to all thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that we have fellowſhip with, and when it ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. Of the Worſhip that is to be attended in Congregational Churches.</head>
               <p>THE End of this Conſtitution of Congregational Churches is the joynt Celebration of the Worſhip of God, herein they differ from civil Societies, that meet together for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of civil affairs.</p>
               <p>The firſt part of Worſhip that is to be attended in the Church of God is Prayer; Prayer which includes in it, beſides Petitions, confeſſions and thankſgivings, is a principal part of Gods Worſhip, Prayer is a part of Gods Worſhip, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.32. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.1. This is to be attended in the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.4. Theſe publick Prayers are to be ordinarily performed by the Teaching Elders; in caſe there be a Vacancy it may be performed by the Ruling Elders, or ſome of the Brethren, but ordinarily the Miniſter is to be the mouth of the People to God, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.4.</p>
               <p>Theſe publick Prayers ought not to be made by the reading of preſcribed forms of Prayer, out of a Book, he that hath not the gift of Prayer, is not fit to be a Miniſter; there may be ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt Caſes wherein it is Lawful for a Man to Pray in a form which they have Learned out of a Book, but the impoſing of ſuch a thing on Men is an addition to Divine Inſtitutions, and the ordinary practiſing of it is of very bad Conſequence; it quenches and ſtifles the Spirit of Prayer, indulges Men in Idleneſs and is very unprofitable to others.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96810:10"/>
               <p>The ſecond part of Worſhip to be performed in the Church, is Singing of Pſalms; this is a Moral Duty not belonging peculiarly to the time of the Old Teſtament, as Chriſt with his Diſciples did pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it; So afterwards <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, Act.</hi> 16. And we have poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive commands for it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13. In the primitive times when God gave to all extraordinary Gifts of his Spirit.</p>
               <p>It was the manner ſometimes for one Man to ſing a <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and the Congregation to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15,16. But now it is moſt proper for us to joyn together in Singing of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> as Chriſt and his Diſciples did, and as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1.</p>
               <p>As the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were wont to Sing the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> ſo (tho we are not forbidden to Sing <hi>Pſalms</hi> of a private compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) it is Lawful for us to Sing the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David</hi> and other Scripture <hi>Pſalms,</hi> the Apoſtle when he directs us to Sing <hi>Pſalms, Hymns</hi> and Spiritual Songs, <hi>Eph. Col.</hi> 3. Hath a manifeſt reſpect to the diviſion of <hi>Davids Pſalms,</hi> ſome things in thoſe <hi>Pſalms</hi> are not ſo ſuteable to our preſent Caſe, ſo it is in what we read, yet thoſe <hi>Pſalms</hi> are very ſuteable for us to meditate upon; and contain in them much Inſtruction and Incouragement, and becauſe they were indicted by the Spirit of God, are more proper to affect our hearts and excite the workings of Grace, then ſuch as are of a private Compoſure.</p>
               <p>A third part of Worſhip is the Preaching and Teaching of the Word; the Preaching of the Word is to be attended to the End of the World, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.20. It is the Duty of Miniſters to Preach the Word, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. A Miniſter is called a Preacher, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14. This is a ſpecial means to advance the Converſion of Sinners and Edification of Saints.</p>
               <p>Altho it be the ſpecial Office and Duty of Teaching Elders, and ordained Miniſters of the Goſpel, yet Preaching being a Moral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is lawful for thoſe, who are not ordained Miniſters, to Preach the Goſpel; Yea, in ſome caſes it is Lawful for ſuch Men who are not devoted to the Miniſtry, provided they have ſuteable abilities.</p>
               <p>The reading of large Portions of Scripture upon the Sabbath Day, which was conſtantly Practiſed by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, is not ſo particularly now required by God, there was great need of it in thoſe Ages, when the World had not the benefit of Preaching; but there is no inſtitution requiring any ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96810:10"/> of us, any further then the Rule of Edification calls for it.</p>
               <p>Miniſters are not bound to obſerve any particular method in their Preaching, they may Preach either by expounding ſome Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scripture, or by raiſing a Doctrine from a particular Text, and applying of it, or by explaining of a Catechiſm, or in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profitable way. Miniſters have Power to Catechiſe their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, not only that they may know their fitneſs to participate at the Lords Table, but alſo in order to their growth in knowledge, tho it may be preſumed that many Perſons are inquiſitive and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet there are many others who are not to be confided in, and the Miniſter hath Power by Virtue of his Paſtoral charge, to ſee that they Learn; reaſon dictates this to be a moſt ſuteable method, as in the Learning of Arts and Languages, ſo in the Learning of the way of ſalvation, the moſt proper and profitable ways of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are to be uſed by Miniſters.</p>
               <p>A fourth part of Worſhip is Baptiſm; this is an ordinance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt himſelf to be a perpetual Ordinance in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, It was publiſhed by <hi>John</hi> before, by Virtue of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, but afterwards declared by Chriſt, to be a ſtanding ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the Church.</p>
               <p>It is very likely that the form afterwards uſed by <hi>John</hi> and his Diſciples was, that they did Baptize in the Name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.5. But ſeeing Chriſt did expreſly command his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles before his aſſention, to <hi>Baptize in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> we have no reaſon to think that the firſt Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Goſpel did uſe any other form, and when we read that the <hi>Samaritans, were Baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, Act.</hi> 8.18. And that <hi>Peter</hi> ordered that <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Company ſhould be Baptized in the Name of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.48. No more ſeems to be intended by it, then their being Baptized according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>The Perſons that are ſent to Adminiſter Baptiſm, are the ſame that are ſent to Preach the Word, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19,20. Tho the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did ſometimes decline it, yet we have reaſon to conclude that they committed it to Inferiour Miniſters; After the Example of Chriſt, who did not commit it to the People, but to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>John</hi> 4.2. Therefore ſuch Preachers as are not ordained Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, are not to Baptize.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96810:11"/>
               <p>Baptiſm may be Adminiſtred either in the Publick Aſſembly or in private, there is no appointment that neceſſitates the publick performance of it, there is nothing in the Nature of the ordinance that doth neceſſitate it; and we find that the Apoſtles and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Men, did it as there was occaſion, both publickly and privately, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.38. and 9.18. and 16.33.</p>
               <p>There is no neceſſity that Perſons be Members of any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation before they be Baptized; Perſons before they be Members of any particular Congregation, may have that qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that gives them a right to Baptiſm. <hi>viz.</hi> Viſible Saintſhip; many that were Baptized in the firſt times did not belong to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation of Chriſtians, and tho many of them did belong to particular <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Congregations or Synagogues, yet ſome did not, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.33.</p>
               <p>Such adult Perſons as make ſuch a profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, as is Morally ſincere, are to be Baptized; as doth appear by the Example of <hi>John,</hi> Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Phillip</hi> and others, who were directed by the Spirit of God; and none were refuſed that did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly tender themſelves to be Baptized.</p>
               <p>Such Infants as are deſcended from the Covenant People of God by either Parent, are to be Baptized, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Such Infants as do deſcend from Parents that are under Church conſures, for immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are not to be denied Baptiſm, becauſe Excommunication doth not cut Men off from the Covenant of God; ſuch Infants as are the Children of Heathens, belonging to the Families of the People of God, are Incorporated into the Covenant and are to be Baptized; when the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Elſe were your Children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, he ſpeaks of them as they come into the World; yet it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not, but when they are taken into the Families of Chriſtians, they do become Holy; ſuch were to be Circumciſed under the Law.</p>
               <p>A fifth part of Worſhip is the Lords Supper; which was inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt a little before his Death, to be a ſtanding Ordinance in the Chriſtian Church; all ſuch Profeſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Chriſtian Faith, as are of blameleſs Converſation, and have knowledge to exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves and diſcern the Lords Body, are to be admitted to the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>Three things are requiſite in order to admiſſion to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; Firſt, Viſible Saintſhip, and that is found in ſuch Perſons; all profeſſors walking blameleſly are Viſible Saints; the Members of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church are often called Saints in the Scripture, who did
<pb facs="tcp:96810:11"/> give no further evidence of their Saintſhip, a Profeſſion of the faith joyned with a good Converſation, is a ſufficient ground for Charity, theſe are marks that we are directed in the Scripture to Judge of Mens Saintſhip by; The Apoſtle did accept of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for Viſible Saints, Men that have theſe Characters, are not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly wicked, therefore they are Viſible Saints; theſe properties are the proper Fruits of Saintſhip, and therefore conſtitute Men Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Saints; ſuch a profeſſion as being ſincere makes a Man a real Saint, being Morally ſincere, makes a Man a Viſible Saint. That whereby Godly Men do make their Saintſhip Viſible, does make Men Viſible Saints, <hi>viz.</hi> A profeſſion of the truth and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
               <p>A ſecond requiſite is, that they be not ſcandalous; a Man that is really and viſibly Godly may fall into a ſcandal, and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count be forbidden to participate at the Lords Table, but when their Converſation is good, they cannot be hindred upon that Account.</p>
               <p>A third requiſite is, that they have knowledge to examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and diſcern the Lords Body; for the want of this Infants are denied the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Adult Perſons that are fit to be admitted into the Church, are to be admitted to the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>All Adult Perſons that are fit to be admitted into the Church, ordinarily have all thoſe qualifications requiſite to the participation of the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>They make profeſſion of the true Faith and are of good Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, they have knowledge of the principles of Religion, and ſo are able to examine themſelves, and if any of them ſhould not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Nature of that ordinance, they may ſoon be ſufficiently informed.</p>
               <p>Two things are evident in the practiſe of the Apoſtles, one is, that they readily admitted ſuch into the Church, as made a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Chriſtian Faith, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 6. We never read that ever they denied Admiſſion to any Man or Woman that made that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; the other is, that all that were thus received by them, were admitted to the Lords Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.24. They made no diſtinction of the Adult Members of the Church, into Communicants and Non-Communicants.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are commanded by God to participate of the Lords Supper, are to be admitted to the Lords Supper, but all profeſſors that have a good Converſation and Knowledge are commanded by God to participate in the Lords Supper; if Men have not theſe Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications
<pb facs="tcp:96810:12"/> they are not obliged immediately to participate in the Lords Supper, for it would be a ſin if they ſhould: But having theſe Qualifications they are bound, provided they have opportunity. Chriſt has laid this Law upon Profeſſors, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24,25. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons here commanded are not only true Believers, then none can do it with a good Conſcience but thoſe that know themſelves to be true Believers; then the Church Authority can require none but true Believers to come, the Perſons therefore required to partake are ſuch profeſſors as carry it inoffenſively, and if ſuch are bound to come, the Church is bound to receive them, they may not hinder any Man from doing his Duty.</p>
               <p>There can be no juſt cauſe aſſigned, why ſuch Men ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from coming to the Lords Supper, they are not to be debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for not giving the higheſt evidence of ſincerity; There never was any ſuch Law in the Church of God, that any ſhould be debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Church Priviledges becauſe they did not give the higheſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſincerity, nor for want of the Exerciſe of Faith; it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to believe Men to be viſible Saints from their Infancy till they be forty or fifty years of Age, and yet not capable of coming to the Lords Supper, for want of the Exerciſe of Faith; they are not to be denied becauſe of the weakneſs of Grace, they that have the leaſt Grace need to have it Nouriſhed and Cheriſhed.</p>
               <p>Such Adult Perſons as are worthy to be admitted into the Church, or being in the Church are worthy to be continued without cenſure, are to be admitted to the Lords Supper; it is utterly unreaſonable to deny the Adult Members of the Church, the Lords Supper, and yet not lay them under cenſure; If they are guilty of any ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence as to be denyed the Lords Supper, why are they not cenſured? If they are not worthy to be cenſured, why are they kept from the Lords Supper?</p>
               <p>There are ſome Scriptures that have been thought to hold forth a need of ſomewhat further, in order to participation in the Lords Supper, which if they be examined will be found to be ſtrained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Import of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, I will tell you what the Lord hath done for my Soul, hence it is argued, that Men ſhould give an Account of the manner of their Converſion, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their Admiſſion; but if it ſhould be granted that <hi>David</hi> doth reſpect the work of Regeneration, doth it follow becauſe he was willing to talk of it, that they might make a Law to bind him to do it in the Synagogue, or doth it follow that <hi>David</hi> offered to do it in order to his joyning with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. They
<pb facs="tcp:96810:12"/> were pricked at the heart, before they were admitted into the Church, but let it be conſidered that many others were joyned to the Chriſtian Church, of whom we read no ſuch thing, and here is no living Rule that others muſt declare that they are pricked at the heart before their Admiſſion; yea it is certain, that theſe did not declare their trouble, in order to their Admiſſion into the Church, but in order to their Direction; yea, it doth not appear that theſe Men were under a work of Converſion at this time, they might be Godly Men before, the thing that ſtung them was a National ſin, which in probability, they had no hand in; For the greater part of them, were ſtrangers, come up to keep the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> and were greatly affected with the ſin which the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> were guilty of in Crucifying of Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26,27. The Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> refuſed to admit <hi>Paul</hi> to their Communion, till they were informed by <hi>Barnabas,</hi> of his Converſion, but it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that <hi>Paul</hi> did then deſire to participate with them in the Lords Supper, poſſibly it might be only in hearing of the Word and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the reaſon why they were unwilling to receive him, was not any doubt whether his Converſion was ſincere, but whether he was a Chriſtian; As if in a Popiſh Country, one who had been a violent Perſecutor ſhould Eſſay to joyn himſelf to a Proteſtant Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it would be no wonder if they ſhould be affraid of him, until they were informed that he was become a Proteſtant; this is no foundation to require of all that joyn to the Church, an Accout a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the manner of their Converſion. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. Men are requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ready to give an Anſwer to every one that asketh them a reaſon of the hope that is in them; but here by the reaſon of the hope that is in them, we are not to underſtand their experiences of the Grace of God, but the grounds of their Faith, the reaſon why they did believe the Chriſtian Doctrine? This is evident, becauſe he is ſpeaking of Perſecution, <hi>v.</hi> 14. and becauſe he directs them to give their Anſwer with meekneſs and fear.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Here it may be enquired, whether ſuch Perſons as have a good Converſation and a Competent Knowledge, may come to the Lords Supper, with a good Conſcience, in caſe they know themſelves to be in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Condition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They may and ought to come, tho they know themſelves to be in a Natural Condition; this Ordinance is inſtituted for all the Adult Members of the Church who are not ſcandalous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be attended by them; as no Man may neglect Prayer, or hearing the Word, becauſe he cannot do it in Faith, ſo he may not neglect the Lords Supper.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96810:13"/>
               <p>The Lords Supper is Inſtituted to be a means of Regeneration, it is not appointed for the Converting of Men to the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for only ſuch as are Converted may partake of it; but it is not only for the ſtrengthening of Saints, but a means alſo to work ſaving Regeneration.</p>
               <p>There be many, according to the Ordinance of Chriſt, to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords Supper, who are not Regenerate, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.1,2. The Kingdom of Heaven is like ten Virgins, five of them were Wiſe, and five Fooliſh, and it can have no other immediate end re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting theſe, but their Converſion; the end of all Ordinances is ſalvation, and therefore to theſe Men it muſt be Regeneration, for without it, they cannot be ſaved.</p>
               <p>This Ordinance hath a proper tendency to draw ſinners to Chriſt; in this Ordinance there is a particular Invitation to ſinners, to come to Chriſt for Pardon, here is an affecting Repreſentation of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Chriſts ſufferings, here is a Seal whereby the Truth of the Goſpel is confirmed, all which are very proper to draw ſinners to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>If the Lords Supper be only for the ſtrengthening of Saints, then they who are not Saints do profane the Ordinance, when they do partake, and it is not Lawful for them to partake, and then they that do not know themſelves to be Saints, don't know that it is Lawful for them to partake, and ſo far as any Man hath ſcruples about his Saintſhip, he muſt proportionably have ſcruples about the Lawfulneſs of his Participation, and ſo Sacrament Days which ſhould be Days of Comfort, will become Days of Torment.</p>
               <p>All other Ordinances are appointed for Regeneration, Prayer, hearing the Word, Baptiſm; ſo likewiſe the cenſures are, that the Soul may be ſaved in the Day of the Lord Jeſus; they are to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mens Regeneration, in caſe they be not Converted already, and it would be ſtrange if the Lords Supper alone ſhould not be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that end, whereas it hath a proper tendency thereunto, and many that come to that Ordinance by the appointment of Chriſt, ſtand in as much need of it, as thoſe that partake of other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
               <p>A ſixth part of the Worſhip is Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, theſe were appointed in the time of the Old Teſtament, and are to continue in uſe unto the end of the World, it doth evidently appear, both from the Writings of the <hi>Jews</hi> and likewiſe from the Scripture, that the <hi>Jews</hi> did make uſe of Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, <hi>John</hi> 4.34,35. <hi>John</hi> 3.22. and 12.42. And it is evident, that theſe cenſures were accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96810:13"/> to Divine Inſtitution, from <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.17,18. Chriſt doth not here make a new Inſtitution for the Goſpel Church, for that Church was not yet in Being, but he urges them to the practiſe of an Old Inſtitution; if it be enquired where we find any ſuch Inſtitution in the Old Teſtament, I Anſwer, in that expreſſion which we often find in the Old Teſtament, that they ſhould be cut off from <hi>Iſrael, Gen.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.14. When one Brother is required to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove another, and in caſe of Incorrigibleneſs to complain to the Church, that command doth not only bind the Brethren of the ſame Congregation, but alſo the Brethren of any other Congregation; for there lies the ſame Bond upon us according to opportunity, not to ſuffer ſin in others, as well as in the Members of the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
               <p>There is no need of a particular Inſtitution, who ſhall have the Power of Judgment, to determine whether a Perſon be to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured or not; it is a part of Rule, and where God appoints Rulers in his Church, he appoints that they ſhall Judge theſe matters; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Chriſt appoints a Paſtor to be a Ruler in the Church; he expreſſes it by having Power of binding and looſing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19.</p>
               <p>A Perſon that is under Church cenſures, is not thereby cut off from his Memberſhip, he ſtands in a Brotherly relation to other Members of the Church, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.15. Lying under offence and under cenſure for his offence, doth not deprive him of his Viſible Saintſhip, therefore his Children are to be Baptized.</p>
               <p>Such offences as are of a more Heinous Nature, don't call for Church cenſures, provided there be a ſuteable Spirit of Repentance; if the end of cenſures be obtained, there is no occaſion for them; Perſons under the ſentence of Excommunication, are not only to be debarred from the Lords Supper, but alſo to be exclued from the familiar Society of the People of God; where there is no ſpecial Bond, we are not to have that Society with them, that we may have with Heathens, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9,12.</p>
               <p>To this Act of Worſhip appertains Abſolution, when the Perſon that hath offended doth manifeſt a Spirit of Repentance, whether he has been cenſured or not, he is to be acquited.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Act of Worſhip is the Bleſſing of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; there is a Bleſſing of Men by way of ſupplication, that may be performed by any Perſon, and there is a Bleſſing by way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, this is pronounced in the Name of God; this is either extraordinary, by way of prediction, ſo the Patriarchs did bleſs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96810:14"/> their Children, and others endued with a Prophetical Spirit, did bleſs the People, as <hi>Moſes;</hi> or elſe ordinary, pronounced in Gods Name by ordinary Miniſters; this may either be pronounced by way of aſſertion, as when the Miniſter doth ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are they that hear the Word of God and do it;</hi> Or in way of ſupplication, as when he ſaith, <hi>The Grace of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you;</hi> Yet this is more then a Prayer, <hi>Viz.</hi> A Declaration in Gods Name what ſhall come to paſs, and therefore it muſt be underſtood in ſuch a way as is according to Gods Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.34. <hi>God appointed the Prieſts of Old to Bleſs the People,</hi> Numb. 6.23. And this work ſeems to be a common work to the reſt of the Levites, who were teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 10.8. There is no need of any new Inſtitution in the Goſpel, impowring Miniſters to bleſs in the Name of God, it being a proper part of the work of a Miniſter; Chriſt by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Miniſters, hath appointed Men to bleſs the People; yet that ſeems to be Inſtituted, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.12,13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.5.</p>
               <p>Such Men as are Preachers of the Goſpel, yet not ſeparated to that work by Ordination, have no Power to bleſs the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, becauſe this depends meerly upon Inſtitution, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not to be done, but according to Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>Miniſters being appointed to bleſs Authoritatively in the Name of God, it is utterly improper for them to ſpeak in the firſt Perſon, including themſelves, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.24. It is alſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for them to Bleſs the Church of God, that are diſperſed all over the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96810:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Of Churches conſiſting of Divers Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</head>
               <p>A Church conſiſting of Divers Congregations, is a Society of Divers Congregational Churches, joyning together accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods appointment, for the conſtant carrying on of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip of God; ſuch Churches are acknowledged in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Part of Proteſtant Churches; but ſome in latter times do make a Queſtion whether there be any ſuch Churches.</p>
               <p n="1">That there are National Churches, does appear, <hi>Firſt,</hi> from the light of Nature, the light of Nature teaches us, that Man was made for the Worſhip of God, that Man is fitted for Society, and the great end why he is ſo, is, that in Society he may carry on the Worſhip of God, and as the light of Nature teaches us, that leſſer Societies ought to carry on the Worſhip of God in Conjunction, ſo that Kingdoms and Countrys ſhould joyn together in promoting and advancing the Worſhip of God; it is moſt agreeable to the light of Nature, that they that are one People, ſhould Unite toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in carrying on Gods Worſhip, and ſhould have Power to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and govern the ſeveral parts of that Body. Nature teaches, that every Kingdom ſhould ſee that the Worſhip and Ordinances of God, be attended in the ſeveral Congregations therein.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi>dly,</hi> From Gods appointing the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> to be one Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.38. And God has not appointed any new forms of Churches in the times of the New Teſtament; there are no other kinds of Churches appointed now; Congregational Churches are no new kind of Churches, but according to the Old Inſtitution; for ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y Synagogue of the <hi>Jews</hi> was a Congregational Church, they had Eccleſiaſtical Rule and Government in them; they are called Churches by Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. That the Old Teſtament Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution doth continue ſtill, appears partly becauſe the Chriſtian Churches of the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſubordinate to the National Church of the <hi>Jews;</hi> they were Members of the National Church, and did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ordinances; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>fore by Inſtitution, Chriſtian
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96810:15"/> Congregations are not abſolute, but Subordinate to a National Church; it is further evident, becauſe the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> National Church did not ceaſe as their Ceremonies did, becauſe their Date was out, but becauſe they rejected Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. Had they kept Gods Covenant, they would have continued a National Church to this Day.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi>ly,</hi> From the Publick Covenant that is between God and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing People; God made a Publick Covenant between him and the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> wherein he engages publick Proſperity unto them, upon condition of their obedience; and all profeſſing Countries are under the ſame Covenant for ſubſtance; the promiſes, and ſo the threatnings declared are of force unto the end of the World, and we have the like encouragement to obedience that they had, and are in the like danger in caſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſobedience.</p>
               <p>God deals with profeſſing Countrys at this Day according to the Tenor of that Covenant, thoſe promiſes will never be out of Date to the end of the World, God makes the ſame to <hi>Iſrael</hi> with reſpect to the time of their Reſtoration, this abundantly Witneſſeth that every Chriſtian Nation is a Church; if God hath made a Covenant with them upon condition of obedience, then they are a Society in Covenant with God, then they are one body in Covenant with God, and the whole hath Power over the parts, and they are inveſted with ſufficient Authority to ſee the Covenant kept: If they were in Covenant, and had not Power to make the ſeveral parts to keep Covenant, the Covenant would be a ſnare to them; particular Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties might bring guilt upon them, and they would have no Power to remove it; if they be all engaged in one individual Covenant, the Country hath Power to regulate all Maleadminiſtrations that any of the parts are guilty of, if they are in one individual Covenant, they are as one body Expouſed by God, the People of God, the flock of Chriſt, and therefore one Church; here is all that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be a Church, therefore ſuch a People are a Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4<hi>ly,</hi> From the promiſes that God hath made of making Gentile Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be his People; God did not only promiſe to ſet up ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Churches among the Gentiles, but to take whole Nations into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22. And it is expreſly foretold by Chriſt, that whole Nations ſhould receive the Goſpel, and become Churches, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.43. Yea, the Scripture declareth that when <hi>Iſrael</hi> is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, they ſhould be in the ſame Covenant as formerly, the ſame promiſes are made to them in <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>iel,</hi> as the Fruits of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as were made to them in <hi>Deutrenomy;</hi> and if the whole <hi>Jewiſh</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96810:15"/> Nation will be one Church, when they are reſtored, then it will be ſo with every other Chriſtian Nation, the difference between <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> is now aboliſhed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe the ſupream Eccleſiaſtical Authority doth not lye in particular Congregations; if there be no National Church, then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ngregation is abſolute and independant, and not reſponſable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y higher Power: This is too Lordly a principle, it is too ambitious a thing for every ſmall Congregation to arrogate ſuch an uncontroulable Power, and to be accountable to none on Earth; this is neither a probable way for the Peace of Churches, nor for the ſafety of Church Members; appeals <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> admitted in all Kingdoms; and it is more probable that in a wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Country, Perſons may be found that may rectify the Miſcarria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then that particular Congregations will not miſcarry; this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſs of particular Congregations is a dignity that the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches did not enjoy, this is not the common Priviledge of Goſpel Churches; the primitive Churches were under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apoſtles, and it ſeems that God gave them this Power, becauſe the ordinary way of Government could not then be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the greater part of all Gentile Nations lying in their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm.</p>
               <p n="1">Obj. 1. <hi>We don't find in the New Teſtament, any National Church among the Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The reaſon of that is, not that National Churches are not according to the mind of God, in the Days of the New Teſtament, but becauſe there was no Nation that did receive the Chriſtian faith. Tho there were many Congregations gathered among the Gentiles, yet there were very few of them, comparitively, that did entertain the Goſpel; the bulk of all the Gentile Nations, lay in their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, during all that time that we have the Hiſtory of in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">Obj. 2. <hi>God hath not appointed in the New Teſtament any National Officers, as the High Prieſt in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>nor any National place of VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>therefore there is no National Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To have one National Officer over the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>le, is not eſſential to the being of a National Church; <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a National Church, when they had no ſuch National Officers, while the firſt Born did Exerciſe the Office of the Prieſts, before the ſeparation of the Levites to that work. There be ſeveral ſorts of civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, none of which are eſſential to a Republick. The being of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church doth not neceſſitate this or that form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96810:16"/> If there be a National Church, it follows that there muſt be ſome to Rule over the whole, but that this Power ſhould reſide ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſolely, or principally in one Man, doth not follow at all. It was ſuteable to the State of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, that there ſhould be one ſupream Officer to be a Type of Chriſt; but now there being no ſuch occaſion, the Church may be governed witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> any ſuch.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To have one National place of Worſhip, is but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cidental to a National Church; <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a National Church in <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet had no National place of Worſhip; all the Worſhip of God, beſides that which was tipical, might be attended in their Synagogues. The not having a National place of Worſhip, is no hinderance to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Governed by a Nati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Authority. There may be a National Government as well wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, as with a National place of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>This National Church is to be divided into provincial, and thoſe again ſubdivided into Claſſical. The Light of Nature teaches us to make ſuch Diviſions of great Political Bodies, that Government may be more eaſily managed. Natural prudence teaches Men in the civil State, to make ſuch Subordination of Courts of Juſtice, for the benefit of the Common Wealth. This is according to the Counſel which was given to <hi>Moſes,</hi> by his father in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw, and approved by God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. By the ſame Rule that the whole is to Rule over the parts, the greater parts are to Rule over the leſſer parts, for a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part, is an whole reſpecting the leſſer parts into which it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. A County is a part with reſpect to a Province, but an whole with reſpect to the ſeveral Congregations therein, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly may Exerciſe Government over them; yet with Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to that Authority that is over the whole. A gradation both in Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Authority is founded in the very Law of Nature.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>If we grant a National Church under the Goſpel, we may as well grant an Oecumenical Church: thoſe that plead for the Juriſdiction of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, refer things at laſt to the Judgment of an Oecumenical Synod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is no ſuch thing as an inſtituted Oecumenical Church; there is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lick Church, but that Notes all thoſe that profeſs the true Religion; but there is no Inſtituted Oecumenical Church, for the ſeveral Chriſtian Nations are not in the ſame Covenant; they are indeed in the ſame ſpecial Covenant, but not in the ſame individual Covenant; ſo it is here, one Nation may keep Covenant, while other Nations brack Covenant.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96810:16"/>
               <p>Neither is there any Inſtitution for Oecumenical Synods; if they could convene, they have no Authority; their conſultations might be of ſome uſe to others, but they have no Authority. A National Synod, is the higheſt Eccleſiaſtical Authority upon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. Of the Government of National Churches.</head>
               <p>SUch Proteſtants as have acknowledged National Churches, have been divided about the form of Government to be practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; ſome of them are for a mixt Government, partly by Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops, and partly by Synods, ſo the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Some have Governed by a Synod alone, ſo the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and this Government ſeems moſt Conſonant to the Word of God. Synods have been generally acknowledged in all Churches, but upon differing grounds, ſome have founded them upon that Rule of prudence, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.66. <hi>In the Multitude of Counſellers there is ſafety,</hi> but if they be grounded upon this, they have no other work but to counſel and adviſe, and they can have no Authority; all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Authority does depend upon an Inſtitution, their Authority muſt be derived from God. Some do found it upon that Example, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. But this was not properly a Synod, this was not the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Elders of many Churches, but of the Apoſtles and Elders of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> together with the Brethren; yet no doubt but the Apoſtles, who were part of that Aſſembly, had the Power of a Synod. But the Foundation of Synods is partly that Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Covenant, which is between God and his People, partly his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution in the Old Teſtament, and partly the Rules laid down for the Churches to walk by in the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This Publick Covenant ſhews that the whole muſt Rule the parts. The Rule and Government doth fundamentally belong unto the Church; the Church hath a right to Govern it ſelf. Thus it is Originally with all Nations as to their civil Government, ſo alſo as to Eccleſiaſtical, and therefore the Exerciſe of this Government muſt be in the hands of ſome that do legally repreſent the whole; if it be not by ſome that repreſent the whole, then the whole do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96810:17"/> not Govern, the Rulers muſt be the repreſentation of the whole Church. Thus it is with a Synod, they are either the Elders of the ſeveral Churches, if the Country be not too Numerous, or ſuch as are choſen by the Elders, if the Country be large and numerous, and theſe are a legal repreſentation of the Churches; the Elders of the Churches are choſen to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Office, to be Rulers of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Churches, and in caſe there be need. They have Power to ſelect out of themſelves, ſuch a Company as may conveniently meet, with whom their Power ſhall be entruſted. The Light of Nature teaches, that the Government muſt be committed to ſuch a Number, as ſhall not be uncapable by reaſon of their Number, to aſſemble and diſcourſe together, for otherwiſe the Government of the Church would not be a thing practicable.</p>
               <p>Thus it is not with Biſhops, they do not legally repreſent the Church; for they are not choſen by the Church, they are not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons elected by the Church to Act in their behalf, but are put into their Office by civil Authority; and how can they repreſent the Church who do not deſire any Authority from the Church; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, their Office is not of Divine Inſtitution, and how can they who are not of Divine appointment, legally repreſent the Church? Thoſe whoſe Office is not acknowledged in the Law of God, cannot legally repreſent the Church of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was Governed by a Counſel of ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two Perſons. Some are of Opinion that the <hi>Jews</hi> had both an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and a civil <hi>Sanedrim,</hi> this is evident, that in Chriſts time they had a Councel that did conſiſt in a great part of the Prieſts, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.6. and 22.30. And that God appointed the Prieſts and other Judges to joyn together in hearing of Controverſies, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.17. So alſo that there was an aſſembly of the chief of the Prieſts and Levites, appointed by <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> to hear Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8. And that the High Prieſt was over them in thoſe Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, <hi>v.</hi> 11. By theſe things it is evident, that the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was Governed by an Aſſembly of the Principal Men of the Church. Chriſt Jeſus doth approve of their form of Government that was in his time, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.2,3. By Prieſts, Scribes, Phariſees. By this it is not only evident, that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a National or Provincial Church, by an Aſſembly of its Principal Elders, is a proper ſuteable and hopeful way; but likewiſe that this way is to be obſerved in Chriſtian Nations, ſeeing no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proviſion is made for their Government; many of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments that God made for the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, do continue in force ſtill, and this among the reſt, no other Proviſion being made
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96810:17"/> yet it does not follow that our Aſſemblies muſt have any ſtanding preſident, as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Aſſemblies had their High Prieſt, who was their preſident, and was a Type of Chriſt; neither does it follow, that we are limitted to the ſame Number that they were, Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances being a ſufficient reaſon for a variation in ſuch caſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The appointment of Chriſt, that Teaching and Ruling Elders ſhould Govern the Church, ſhews the Power of Synods; theſe are appointed by Chriſt to be the Rulers of the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. There are no other appointed to be Rulers of the Church ſince the Age of the Apoſtles, therefore the Government of the National Church muſt be in their hands; none but they have any Intereſt in the Publick Government; there is no Warrant from the Word of God to intruſt the Government in the hands of any others, and there is ſufficient Warrant for them, to take upon them the Government of the National Church, and this by Virtue of their Office. If there be a Publick Covenant, every Church is bound in Conjunction with others to ſee the Covenant kept, and their Rulers, with whom their Power is intruſted, are bound by Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their Office, to joyn with others to ſee their Covenant kept; ſo that their Acting in a ſynod, is not by Virtue of any New Office. A Miniſter by Virtue of his Miniſterial function, hath Power in Conjunction with others, to Govern the National or Provincial Church.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>If Miniſters have a Bond upon them, to joyn with others in the Rule of the National or Provincial Church, then they ſeem in their own Perſons to be bound to attend that Service; which if all ſhould do in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synods, the Synods would be ſo large a Body, that they could not Diſcourſe together, and it would be an intollerable prejudice to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, being much deprived of their Labours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Power of Intruſting delegates is Warranted by the Light and Law of Nature, there being a neceſſity of it for the good Government of Societies, and there is no neceſſity of a particular Inſtitution in this caſe; the neceſſity of humane affairs does require that Government be intruſted with ſuch a Number that it may be managed to advantage to the Publick, neither is there any hazard of being involved in guilt by ſuch a method; a ſelect Number of the moſt Prudent and Holy of the Elders, are as likely to Govern the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96810:18"/> Church according to the mind of God, as the whole Body of the Elders of a Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. Of the Power of Synods.</head>
               <p>THE Power of Synods doth conſiſt principally in theſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are to teach the People, they are to hold forth Light unto the Church, that was a part of the work of the <hi>Sandedrim</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to teach the People the will of God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.2,3. That was the ſpecial work of the Levites, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.10. That Aſſembly mentioned, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. Met together to give Light to the People of God.</p>
               <p>It is very meet that Synods do Publiſh confeſſions of faith, not only to bear Teſtimony to the World, and other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kingdoms, of their acknowledging the Truth, but eſpecially to be a Light unto the Churches, to guide them in the way of Life, this hath generally been practiſed by the Synods of the reformed Churches.</p>
               <p>They ſhould particularly Vindicate the Truth, and bear their Teſtimony againſt thoſe Errors that are Springing up, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.24. It is meet alſo in caſe of Corruptions in manners, that they do declare what the mind of God is, and Vindicate the Rule; that, if it be poſſible, they may root out ſuch Licentious principles as are prevailing amongſt the People, and adviſe them to repent of ſuch degeneracies as bring down the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God. Yet no Man is bound to receive the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, or practiſe the Rules held forth by a Synod, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are taught by them. A Synod is not infallible, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96810:18"/> therefore no Rule, or Doctrine, is to be taken up on truſt from them; Men do owe that reſpect to a Synod, as 'tis an Ordinance of God, ſolemnly to weigh the Doctrines held forth thereby, but they are not to receive them by an implicite faith; we are bound to prove all things, and if a Man do pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe againſt the Light of his own Conſcience, becauſe a Synod hath otherwiſe determined, he greatly ſins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. The Synod may direct him in a wrong way, and no Man can be bound to any thing that God has forbidden, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are to bind and looſe, to inflict Eccleſiaſtical cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or to take them off; the ſupream Eccleſiaſtical Authority muſt have Power of Judgment, that ſo there may no publick guilt lye upon the Church; if they have not Power of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Particular Perſons may be oppreſſed by the rigour of Presbyteries, and many irregularities committed by the Church, whereby the Country doth become guilty, and there would be no ſufficient way to deliver the Land from guilt. Synods have Power to Admoniſh, to Excommunicate, and deliver from thoſe cenſures, and every Man muſt ſtand to the Judgment of the National Synod, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12.</p>
               <p>They are to Judge in caſe of Complaint; when any Perſon Judges himſelf wronged by the Judgment of a particular Church, and complains to a Synod, they are to hear the caſe, and upon the hearing of it, not to adviſe the Church either to confim the ſentence, or to take it off; but if there be occaſion, they are to take off the ſentence and reſtore the Man unto his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</p>
               <p>They are to judge in caſe of other Complaints; if any Man hath a Complaint againſt another, and cannot obtain a hearing in the Church that he belongs unto, or if the Elders of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church be Complained of for any Male-Adminiſtration, or if a Church with the Elders be complained of for Hereſie, or other ſcandalous Corruption, the Synod is to hear and Judge the caſe, and they may not only cenſure particular Perſons, but whole Churches alſo in caſe of need.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96810:19"/>
               <p n="3">3. Synods have Power to overſee the calling of Perſons to the Miniſtry, and to appoint thoſe who ſhall examine them; if the Synod have the Government of the Church in their hands, tho they ſhould not abridge Congregations of their Liberty, yet they ſhould ſee that Churches Act regularly, and that none ſhould be ſet in the Miniſtry but ſuch as are duely qualified, therefore it belongs them to appoint meet Perſons to examine ſuch as are called to the Miniſtry, and to teſtify their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the laying on of hands, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p>The appointing of Ceremonies of Worſhip is properly the work of Jeſus Chriſt; the making of orders concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal concernments of the Church, is properly the work of the Civil Magiſtrate; but the appointment of ſuch as ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee the calling of Perſons to the Miniſtry, doth properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Eccleſiaſtical Authority.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96810:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
